[SPEAKER_00]: It's another question.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's Bhante.
[SPEAKER_00]: I seek to free myself from attachment to my identity, above all, my gender.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is from a woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_00]: My life has been steeped in sexism, where womanhood is cast as frail, foolish, vain, inferior.
[SPEAKER_00]: At times I let such words drift past me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mere echoes of ignorance, but other times they wound me deeply, making me resent my own birth.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know this attachment to identity is dukkha, yet detachment eludes me.
[SPEAKER_00]: How does one remain unmoved when prejudice is not mere illusion, but rooted in biological differences that others scorn?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is my reasoning flawed, or is true equanimity beyond reach?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not beyond reach, no, but it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to reach it, you might have to give up more that you're willing to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because... See, the world can think one thing or the other thing about your birth, caste, clanhood, gender,
[SPEAKER_01]: But, fundamentally, the only reason that praise and blame affects you, is because you're taking it up as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, each time you feel affected because somebody said something negative about your gender, is because you're taking up their gender as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: As also, how do I take the gender?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do I take it up?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I just say no to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, you can, but that won't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because taking it up, it's not like a conscious, repetitive mental decision that you just sit one day and say, today I'll decide to take it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you take it up through your acts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, are you taking up your body as the basis of pleasure, as the basis of ownership, as the basis of proliferation of desires, sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches?
[SPEAKER_01]: You are taking up the ownership of whatever that body is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever that body is deemed to be by others in the society.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean, like, you can find equanimity, but you need to basically, as the Buddha said, you need to be developed in regard to your own body, internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you need to fully abandon the slightest traces of ownership that would have been proliferated and maintained through the acts of desire, your will, control, safety that you find in the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why the reflections the Buddha was recommending, it's like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to regard your own body internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether others approve of it or not, whether they praise your gender or not, you yourself need to regard it as a... oh, this is a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every time I give in to the physical desires, physical acts of distraction and so on, I am accepting it at a face value.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if I wish to not be moved by praise or blame directed towards my external form, I will be, because I've taken it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to go deep in order to basically uproot that trap that you keep taking up at face value, mistakenly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whether the whole world praises you or blames you, it won't be a problem, because it's like, literally, there's nothing to do with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're praising something that has circumstantially arisen, or they're blaming something that has circumstantially arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only reason you're moving... you... you're being moved by it now is because you are very much... have taken it up and you don't know how to let go of it because you think letting go of it is on some sort of level of some determination, decision that you need to make in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the purification of your acts that perpetuate the ownership, perpetuate desire, perpetuate the basis of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm accepting this body because it serves me for this or that when I want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to see how far you want to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you make yourself liable to those... Yeah, to praise and blame, to the worldly winds, as I should say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of delighting in your body, taking it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Taking it up, delighting in it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's not that praise and blame is the cause of your issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's the secondary issues that arise on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If your body is not taken up through the careless actions rooted in greed, aversion, distraction...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even, as I said, even if you haven't made a conscious decision to not be bothered by what others say, you won't be bothered by what others say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not yours anymore, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no identification with it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, this person who has the question recognizes that identification with the body is the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, to me, it sounds as if that they still hope that there is something they can just do on top of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will unplug that identification.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, you gotta undo everything that you have now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your entire relationship internally with your own body has to be rewritten.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it just feels easier for people to just, well, no, let's just address the society and change everyone's mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: About gender, or about caste, or about whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... that's just the extension of the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you get in your way, even if you get everybody to respect you for where you are, however you were born, you're still taking it up gratuitously.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're taking up that which has... which is circumstantial reason, that which does... is gonna... is gonna lead to... destruction and disintegration.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are still taking it up there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if now you're not affected by the words of others, in regard to your body, or gender, or whatever, you'll be affected by something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is out there in the world that you are... you have no control over, even if you get some degree of everybody agreeing, you know, how to talk about it, how to address it, what to think about it, it's always going to be something else that's going to be at odds with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's not gender that bothers you, it's going to be something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But fundamentally, it's all rooted in the problem of taking up what is not yours, what cannot even be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you refuse to give it up,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead, you want to tailor the environment to keep supporting it and not contradicting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's not one form, like the Buddha said, there's not one type of form that doesn't cause... well, that's not suffering when one's delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because it's subject to change from the very beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if one is not delighted... And it always remains, see, like, even if you get the whole society, say, to approve of the way you were born, and everybody to praise it even, the lingering possibility always remains that somebody might not do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already going to reveal you the whole weight that rides on it, even... it's going to basically make you feel just the possibility that somebody might still disapprove of you,
[SPEAKER_01]: It will bother you as much as the actual disapproval used to bother you, because it reveals the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unownable, yet you refuse to let go of it, because it's too terrifying to think of, well, how would I live without desires, without satisfying my desires, without giving in to the distractions?
[SPEAKER_01]: How will I live without using this body to get what I want?
[SPEAKER_01]: That just feels like, oh, well,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like an abyss, as the suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_01]: The idea of not following physical desires, not acting out of body and wholesomely, to people that are like householders and not practicing restraint, that feels like a sudden precipice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It feels like the end of life almost.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the only reason it feels like that is because you refuse to even consider the alternative of giving it all up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, as I said, you're left in this state of conflict of this which is unownable, that I know I shouldn't be identified with, I can't help by being identified with, and I kind of recognize that's why I'm bothered by things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... because being elated on account of praise, it's equal bother.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually even worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, if somebody's just criticizing you, it outlines the problem for you, the problem of identification with the body that's being fully criticized and attacked.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody praises you, that's even stickier, even slimier, even harder to get rid of your own delight in that acceptance.
[SPEAKER_00]: The praises, it traps you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, because, see, on top of already not being able to not accept the body at the face value, the senses at the face value,
[SPEAKER_01]: The extension of the approval of that, someone's praise, is just going to be twice as much of acceptance now, that you just can't help.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why it's like, oh, I should actually be more concerned about being praised, than about being criticized on account of my immutable characteristics that I'm born with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because being criticized just outlines the extent of the body they have no control over.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want it to be this way, but if I'm affected, means I'm taking it up in other ways, and now that I'm affected.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a result of that, you get to see that more clearly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But praise...
[SPEAKER_00]: But if all you're getting is praise... Yeah, it fools you, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: It fools you, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no reason to really dig deep.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's kind of the practical purpose of the precept of beautification.
[SPEAKER_01]: And embellishing of your form, you know, clothing, dresses, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... because, see, when people are dependent on their presentation of this body towards others, they're going to feel equally anxious, equally undermined, if they go in the public without the makeup, without the nice clothes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now, what others think about it, affects me to my core.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, it shows you how deeply unownable that which you so thoroughly take to be yours is, this body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, giving up the beautification might seem like a random thing, but actually, for many people, they do depend on their presentation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the level of how far their identity has sort of proliferated.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by not making yourself presentable in what you deem an agreeable way...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't mean, like, go around, like, dirty or filthy.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's quite a clear line between, okay, just be clean or something, but are you now beautifying it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you now emphasizing your form in other ways, in other pleasing ways, to be more accepted or liked or admired?
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that is the extension of that same trying to get that which is deeply not yours, through approval of others, to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: To confirm that that is yours, because I can't help but regard it as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although deep down I know it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why the beautification, the adornment, the presentation in a kind of selective way, those are all your acts and choices and you need to give that up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, oh, look, nobody likes me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody approves of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might even hate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, yeah, now that's revealing even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: That there is no reason for you to entertain the ownership of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it needs beautification and deceit, well, it means that's not what it really is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, even there, the suttas say, like, a young man or a woman should regard their own body in the same way they would regard a dead snake wrapped around their neck.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh!
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if they see themselves in the mirror, they should be like, oh, this is that unappealing form.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that will become more and more apparent if you would have stopped giving in to, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, cover-ups, beautifications, presentations, the way that, you know, the society wants it, or you want society to want it, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you just have like a basic, as I said, common sense, yes, you know, dress up normally, plainly, not trying to increase or emphasize certain aspects of the body that people might deem
[SPEAKER_01]: Nice, just leave it as it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are already distancing yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're already not adding more fuel to that gratuitous identification that you shouldn't have been doing in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keeping it in a proper perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, getting closer to a proper perspective, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to resolve the problem, but it's certainly not going to make it worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not emphasizing the wrong things anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, which you would have been doing only because you refuse to give up the pleasure you get through it and your implicit identification with it.